

Front-end web developer based in London

Website: thomjamesallen.com
GitHub: github.com/tjallen
Email: thomwork@gmail.com

Mobile: 07747 229 007

Summary

I'm a front-end web developer passionate about building **effective**, **user-friendly web experiences**. I've spent the majority of recent years working on the front-end of JS-based web apps, especially **React**, but also have full stack experience (particularly **Node** + **MongoDB** backends using **GraphQL**). I'm always interested in learning new tech however!

History

Zzish, Lead Front-end Developer

Apr 2018 - Feb 2023

Stack: React, Next, Apollo, GraphQL, JavaScript ES6 + TypeScript, Node + Express, MongoDB, Webpack, Pusher, Kubernetes, AWS

Led the front-end team at **Zzish**, an education technology startup who focus on improving education outcomes for teachers and students, primarily via their award-winning teaching platform and assessment tool, **Quizalize**.

- Maintained and implemented new features into existing web apps (<u>Quizalize</u> for student results & differentiated learning and the <u>Quiz Player</u> formative assessment tool) -
- Migrated the stack to more modern/preferred tech (Relay -> Apollo, Flow -> TS, etc).
- Optimised performance where possible, e.g. improving Webpack's bundle splitting, lazy/async loading components, images and GraphQL queries. Some quick wins in early 2023:
 - Optimisation of marketplace GraphQL queries resulted in 35% reduced page load time over previous two months
 - Responsive rebuild of activity dashboard resulted in 12% reduction in bounce rate over prev month
- Led migration of SEO-critical <u>subdomains</u> to self-contained Next apps using SSR taking Lighthouse scores from 50-60 to 90+. Resulted in: (YOY)
 - o 89% reduction in bounce rate
 - o 9% increase in page views per session
 - 25% increase in avg session duration
 - 38% decrease in average page load time

- Led a rebuild of site navigation in mid-2021 with simplified UX, resulting in significant increase in user activity (specifically around class creation - roughly doubled over previous year despite DAU being similar)
- Onboarded and mentored juniors; responsible for code review of FE pull requests, wrote documentation and collaborated on forming team best practices
- Took part in project planning, defining specs, scope, etc, working closely with lead backend & PMs
- Created greenfield web apps like <u>Zzish Insights</u>, making design decisions on front-end architecture.
- Strong focus on user experience and responsive design (mobile-first when possible) working alongside designers, UX
- Worked on back-end & devops tickets as required to ease team workload

Antidote, freelance Front-end Developer

Jan 2018

HTML5, CSS, JavaScript, Greensock.js

Created animated banner ads for client Royal Ascot

ASOS, contract Front-end Developer

May 2017

HTML5, SASS, Gulp, Pug

Contracted at **ASOS**' head office in Camden, building microsites for their brand partnerships with clients **PayPal** and **Hostelworld**. Used Gulp scripts to build from Pug templates to a number of static sites targeting various locales and devices.

Dunnhumby, contract Front-end Developer & QA

Jan 2017

HTML5, XML, CSS, Knockout.js, React

Spent 4 weeks in-house at **Dunnhumby** HQ in Hammersmith, providing QA for **Tesco Groceries**' XML-based banner ads along with workflow consultancy. Prototyped approvals-oriented web app with Knockout.js and responsive ad components with React.

StirPR, contract Front-end Developer

Dec 2016

HTML5, SASS, Foundation

Developed responsive HTML emails for client **Felix** from provided designs.

Antidote, freelance Front-end Developer

May 2016

HTML5, SASS, JavaScript + jQuery, Greensock.js

Worked in-house at **Antidote's** Fitzrovia offices as part of a two developer team, creating banner ads for client **Travel Republic's** summer campaign for a wide variety of destinations and

formats. Created a simple jQuery-based ad viewer to help the agency team quickly review changes & assist with deadlines.

Antidote, freelance Front-end Developer

Jan 2016

HTML5, SASS, JavaScript + jQuery, YouTube API

More work at **Antidote**, for client **Libratone**, creating a custom player module for YouTube 360° videos to be used on a landing page, working to a strict deadline. Refactored first-draft JS into a revealing module pattern and added BEM and 7-1 code conventions. Created documentation for handover.

Phosphor Art, part-time developer

2014 - 2015

WordPress, ExpressionEngine, PayPal API, HTML5, SASS, JavaScript, jQuery

Built responsive promos and landing pages alongside maintaining their existing site. Created HTML email campaigns & email builder, newsletter signup forms etc. Created a responsive online store page prototype using ExpressionEngine.

Stuff & Sense, part-time developer & consultant

2013 - 2014

ExpressionEngine, WordPress, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, ProcessWire

Designed & built the Stuff & Sense company site with a responsive front-end and an ExpressionEngine-based back-end. Provided consultancy services to various clients.

Other work

Freelance web developer

2009 – 2018 primarily

HTML5, CSS + SASS, JavaScript + jQuery, WordPress, React, ExpressionEngine, Grav, Gulp, Webpack

Designed, built and managed sites, landing pages and apps for various small business clients.

Open source developer

2016 – 2018 primarily

JavaScript, React, Redux, MobX, Flux, Electron, Styled Components, Hexo, Gatsby, Jekyll, Vue, Chrome web API, Jest, Enzyme, Mocha, Cosmos, Storybook, Webpack, Travis

- Created open-source apps and contributed to others' repositories.
- Created <u>react-simple-range</u>, an open-source React input slider component released as an NPM package, with 170,000+ downloads. Used semantic-release & Travis CI for automated releases & package publishing when updates are committed to master.
 Collaborated with open-source contributors to add features & fix bugs.

Education & etc

Self-taught developer.

10 GCSEs A* – C, The Ravensbourne School. References available on request